[SPEAKER_03]: So, recently, when I was talking with people in Samādhipa, I was asking and giving some examples of how to talk to your mind, how to communicate.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you were there, so you don't answer the questions.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, if we say, if we remember that the mind is the wild animal that's been contained
[SPEAKER_03]: And now, hopefully, being trained, how do you start talking to it?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you start communicating with it, so that it basically does what you tell it to do, not the other way around?
[SPEAKER_03]: How would you talk to it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Would wishing things,
[SPEAKER_03]: Make it... make it go along your wishes, like you wish your mind to not be upset.
[SPEAKER_03]: Would that make it not upset?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can't talk to it directly, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, it doesn't understand you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how would you be conveying the messages you want to convey?
[SPEAKER_03]: Give me some examples.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which kind of, like, get into, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: What you let it, like, get into, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I mean, yeah, the coarsest example is the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't let it do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: These things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, coarse forms of communication would basically be the precepts already, not letting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can kind of carry that on to, like, just because it wants...
[SPEAKER_01]: I was thinking about this the other day.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not so sure how to put it, but like the fact that there is something present, like a thought, kind of a pressure to think about something, for example, that thought is there, but there is the kind of extra step of the mind being able to, like, like you need to basically give it permission to start
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking about these things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, well, that still kind of comes on the same level, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not letting it or letting it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, precepts sense restraint would be forms of indirect communication.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you are broadly, coarsely conveying a certain message.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the mind still doesn't know why.
[SPEAKER_03]: The animal hasn't learned for itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why it shouldn't be going in those directions, pursuing those pressures.
[SPEAKER_03]: It just knows that it can't go there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you explain to it why?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you tell a dog... How do you get the dog to prefer to stay rather than to go?
[SPEAKER_03]: Rather than to resist?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I mean, you can punish it or you can reward it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just... speaking of a dog, I'm not entirely sure how that would translate, but... Well, no, we're speaking about the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: I just gave the example.
[SPEAKER_03]: It might be more palpable.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you punish the mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you reward it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you need to punish it?
[SPEAKER_03]: When do you need to punish it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, that's... that's where it seems not correct.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's not incorrect.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is an animal that doesn't speak your language.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you make it see something, as you said, through a reward.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, you can't just give it a treat, because that would be... well, that would be undoing your training.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you reward your mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it starts to see for itself, so that you are not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the whole point, obviously, the whole point of this, I mean, I think we said it before, but it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the mind that craves, and you're the one that experiences the results of that pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, mind suffers as well, but it's unaware of it, much like an animal would not have enough self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the mind craves, but then you get to pay the price for that, with the suffering that's felt.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can say, oh, I don't want to crave, and I'll let go of craving, but you're not the one doing the craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not holding, holding the craving, because if you were, you would let it go instantly.
[SPEAKER_03]: You would not need the Buddha's teaching to tell you that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's just the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: The mind keeps
[SPEAKER_03]: The wild dog keeps biting the burning embers, because he doesn't know anything better, because he thinks that will destroy them and free it from the pain, and you are the one being burned by that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you tell that animal?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you teach it to stop doing it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, precepts, establishment and virtues, it's not negotiable, because that would be containing the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: That would be like putting up a fence around, so that at least you know where the animal is, because you're not going to be issuing any commands, right or wrong, if you let the animal loose, if it's gone.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, obviously, you have contained it, but if that's all you did, well, it's still not tamed, so it's still going to be... Sure, it's probably not going to inflict as much suffering as if somebody who is immoral and not virtuous, but nevertheless, it's still a wild animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is still plenty of opportunities within the fenced area to crave, to do stuff, and then you would feel pain on account of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want it to know for itself the craving is bad.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's when the suttas, when it says, like, when a monk becomes an arahant, and his mind is tamed fully, completely, freed from any possibility of craving, it says, oh, it's liberated, and he knows it is liberated.
[SPEAKER_03]: He knows that animal is liberated.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it's like that kind of two-tier knowledge, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, yes, he knows for himself, but he also knows that this thing there, that he's paired with,
[SPEAKER_03]: He is liberated.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's unable to crave.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, he cannot have any fear or concern amidst things, even that are unpleasant, even death, like, you know, among death, he doesn't tremble, because he knows the dog is incapable of doing that ever again.
[SPEAKER_03]: And thus, he can never again experience suffering as a result of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like the most immediate knowledge.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you teach it to stop craving?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, let's look at it practically.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're restrained.
[SPEAKER_03]: You keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: You come across or you come near the mind, the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Through your moods, through your feelings, through the pressures... What do you do?
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you tell it then?
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, you could tell it... drop it or what not, but... that might not necessarily work.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what would be the first thing you would have to do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Say, your mind bothers you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Something's bothering you.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's pressure, annoyance, ill will.
[SPEAKER_03]: What message do you want to tell your mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, keep digging, keep fighting this.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will go away then, and we'll both will be free.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, or no?
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you say?
[SPEAKER_00]: You just got to unresist, you know, calm it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you, you're not, you're not trying to fight it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You relax.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when that thing calms down,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's relaxed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're finding a relaxing situation.
[SPEAKER_04]: But do you need to wait for it to calm down?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or is there... What are you telling me?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I don't think there should... like, you...
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, initially, maybe, yeah, you need to just kind of contain it and say, okay, I'm not gonna... like, it's not allowed... don't allow it to...
[SPEAKER_04]: Think further in this direction, for example.
[SPEAKER_03]: But is it the animal that's thinking?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or is it you?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, I...
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm kind of not used to thinking in terms of this, like, me and the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what we're getting used to.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's obviously a... Well, there's a reason for that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So... Because that is the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, the Buddha did say, the suttas, that you can be
[SPEAKER_03]: Like even an outsider can completely experience dispassion towards the body and remove any ownership, but he can't do it towards the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it has been so close to him for so long and he's been appropriating for so long.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's exactly the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a phenomenon in your experience that you just look past and assume yourself to be, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the original question was...
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so, you don't... Do you need to wait?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I think, before we now go to the original question, let's go to what is the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Here and now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I asked...
[SPEAKER_03]: The other question was basically, so, are you doing the thinking?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or is the animal doing the thinking?
[SPEAKER_00]: Who's doing the thinking?
[SPEAKER_04]: It really depends what you're referring to by the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Citta.
[SPEAKER_03]: I refer to the citta, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're taming the citta, you're not taming anything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: The citta is unliberated, so...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, who's doing the thinking?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where does the thinking come from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Citta or from you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by thinking you don't... What are you referring to by you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else is not citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the thoughts would arise, but then you would overthink them, or intend further upon them, because you don't see the first arising, so to speak, of the phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, first of all, it's like you allow it to be... you're absorbed with something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, that's the first thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you think further on account of being already not aware of attending to certain things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's again, say, like, you stop that.
[SPEAKER_03]: You would stop that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's now, let's say, you're acutely pressured.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ah, let's give a practical example.
[SPEAKER_03]: Somebody, you know, you're full of your will.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have thoughts of cruelty towards that person.
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you thinking those thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or is the mind thinking?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or is citta thinking those thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where are those thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: Who is responsible for them?
[SPEAKER_04]: You.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you are.
[SPEAKER_04]: Fully.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what's the citta's relationship to that?
[SPEAKER_04]: The pressure to think those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the dog is pressuring you, but you don't have to think that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why in that whole, like, Sābhāsava Sutta about, well, all the taints, when it comes to these... No, sorry, that's not Sābhāsava Sutta.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it the one about, you know, the master of thought?
[SPEAKER_03]: Which Sutta is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: 19, 20.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, it was the title, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Stilling of thoughts or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, let's go on and maybe I can... Well, yeah, there's all those points of like refining your thoughts, thinking the opposite thoughts, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's... See, that's what I keep saying to people.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you're doing that because you're trying to get rid of the thoughts, means you're not even seeing your mind to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're blaming the thoughts for the problem and then trying to get rid of them by, you know, sensuality, thinker, subha.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hatred, think, love, or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not in your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're doing it because you're blaming the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, first, you have to not try to get rid of the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the first message you give to the pressuring dog.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, it barks at you, because it also thinks that the thoughts are the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thoughts are scaring the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the animal is barking at the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you go along with it, well,
[SPEAKER_03]: You're affirming what the animal is craving against.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by conveying the message of no, thoughts are not the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: I will endure them, so that the animal can see some space between its own rage and the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the animal is not thinking the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why then, by not trying to get rid of the thoughts, by enduring the pain of the mind,
[SPEAKER_03]: You also get to see where the pain comes from, in case you didn't have that view clarified beforehand, which is the pain comes from the animal that pressures and craves, not the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, why would you think asubha instead of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: What would be the right reason to do so?
[SPEAKER_04]: Teach the mind how to not present that... how to... to teach the mind... how to see things, right, basically?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: To basically... to... to calm it down.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the mind is excited in regard to this thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, in regard to the same thing, you show it the ugly aspects.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, I say.
[SPEAKER_03]: The dog wants to have what's in the bag, and it's really losing its mind over it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you show it what's in the bag, and it's in the bag, and what's in the bag is something absolutely disgusting that it doesn't want to eat.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you're like, okay, no, sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it will walk away and lose interest in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, all those methods, quote-unquote, of countering the thoughts, you're not countering the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're just broadening, basically, the context of perspective, exactly, of the very thoughts, so the animal doesn't go
[SPEAKER_03]: Same with hatred.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's the mind of metta.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not you.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are not thinking metta.
[SPEAKER_03]: You want mind... You want the dog to be in the state of unperturbed friendliness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you have, like, thoughts of ill-will, pressured towards thoughts of ill-will by the animal, well, you broaden the context.
[SPEAKER_03]: Show it the thoughts of the peril of ill-will, the unsatisfactoriness, the limitations, and then the mind will be like, oh, yeah, it's not really worth it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the mind will drop it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't need to drop anything.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, is it like...
[SPEAKER_04]: I was just trying...
[SPEAKER_04]: I was trying to kind of think how to put it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Would be the... What a way of describing how to teach the mind in a general sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because what the mind wants, when it craves, is peace, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: What it's after is peace.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it is going about it the wrong way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that's all it knows.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, what you need to know first is where peace actually comes from.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You need to learn that yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you need to understand where the peace comes from.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, like, you can use, basically, any of these specific things, like asubha and, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: In regard to sensuality, or any of them, would pertain to where the peace actually is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, kind of teaching the mind in, okay, in this instance, the peace is not in the direction of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: The peace is actually in the direction of unsensuality, of disgust.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, see, if you answer the question I was going to ask, that's basically what the treat is.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the reward.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't give it sensuality as a reward, because as I said, that will just agitate it further.
[SPEAKER_03]: But fundamentally, exactly, even citta wants peace.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it pressures towards resolution of central desire, or ill-will, or any hindrance.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you learn what the actual peace is, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: what that right balance is, which you would have learned through simply not trying to get rid of thoughts, or blaming them, or blaming external circumstances, and being able to endure things on the right level, then, when the animal, say... say, is agitated,
[SPEAKER_03]: You presented the the other side of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It calms down and that's where you show it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Look, there is a reward.
[SPEAKER_04]: You tell it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You tell it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a reward.
[SPEAKER_03]: You do the... you do the, basically, the audible sign
[SPEAKER_03]: Sound with with what happens, so it starts to associate too, like the dog.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you use a clicker.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because like initially, that's the thing, it won't even...
[SPEAKER_03]: It won't necessarily, and it won't know where to stop, because you don't know where the peace is.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't know what's actually peaceful.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you do know what's peaceful, you'll see when the animal is within that peace, and then you can tell it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you do that sufficient amount of time, and it will start to see for itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you don't need a clicker anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, fundamentally, yes, exactly, it doesn't want to create.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I once...
[SPEAKER_04]: I was thinking that's like what you relate... relates to what you said as well about the arahant, when he knows it's liberated.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like... Because when you're restraining and everything,
[SPEAKER_04]: It, eh... you know, from one point of view, you're putting like a... you're kind of chaining it down and tying it down.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But really, kind of fundamentally, it's the animal that's chained from the start.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it's kind of chained in regard to... well, because it craves, can't help craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's kind of... it's not liberated in that sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's bothered.
[SPEAKER_03]: I wouldn't use...
[SPEAKER_03]: I wouldn't say it was already chained.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: You chain it through... through precepts and sensory strength.
[SPEAKER_03]: You fence it off.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's already agitated.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like the wild, the wild elephant, the wild dog, whatever, whatever animal you want to use for this contemplation.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's wild.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what it means, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Impulses are controlling it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It acts out of craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: It avoids pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: It seeks pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's absolutely oblivious to neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: It would be fine if it were not your problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the point is, whatever that animal does, you're the one who's going to feel it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like, oh...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, it is in my best interest, and animal's best interest, to train it.
[SPEAKER_03]: To teach it how to not crave.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why the whole, like... Well, obviously, that's why, like, nothing... nothing can match the pleasure of liberation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, like, sotāpatti, anāgāmī, arahant, because it doesn't come... it's not like...
[SPEAKER_03]: You engage with the senses and then you get like a sort of pleasant feedback.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like completely not your own doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the animal that stops craving, but obviously you fully understand that it's entirely your own doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because no wild animal, by any stretch, by any realm, can sort of calm itself down, in a sense to remove the craving, remove the impulse,
[SPEAKER_03]: And acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's self-perpetuating.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anyway, pick an animal in the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: Doesn't matter if it looks peaceful.
[SPEAKER_03]: Internally, every animal, what's in common to that such animal realm in general, it has to act out of impulse.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means it has not enough capacity for that reflection where you can understand its own doing, its own input.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you teach it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now, it's completely...
[SPEAKER_03]: Liberated.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means now, it's completely impossible for you, by any stretch, to experience even possibility of suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the sole reason for suffering was the animal craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And even more, obviously, as the suttas say, it will be impossible for you to be tied to another animal ever again.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's how you reward it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You reward it by thinking thoughts of the factual piece at the right time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not you can be thinking them blindly as a method, but as with the dog training, the timing is important.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where you make an association.
[SPEAKER_02]: Could you also say that it's the teaching
[SPEAKER_02]: The value of neutral feeling only when neutral feeling arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I'm not, obviously, pre-empting it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what you... you're setting up a neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, clicker comes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Through de-agitating the animal, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Through calming it down.
[SPEAKER_03]: Through... through, basically, not acting out of the pressure that the animal is putting on you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, exactly, when there is a neutral feeling established,
[SPEAKER_03]: You show that factual recognition.
[SPEAKER_03]: You think it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You recognize it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, obviously, anything you see, smell, taste, touch, and think, is what animal experiences.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's where your responsibility comes in.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, you know, if everything is already anatta, then nobody kills, nobody... No.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you choose sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, thoughts, which means you choose to keep the animal wild or tame it on account of following suitable sight, sound, smell, taste, touches or unsuitable, as the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by thinking factually thoughts of restraint, relinquishment, withdrawal from unwholesome, the benefit of that
[SPEAKER_03]: You are putting those things in front of an animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you are familiarizing it with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it will... it will get to see it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will get to learn it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will get to associate it for itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's when you know your work is done.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you don't have to keep putting it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, the animal also prefers non-craving, non-agitation, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then it's like, okay, my work's done now.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a tendency to ignore the neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: It undermines that reward, like the ability to... Well, yeah, I mean... becoming indolent towards...
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's... whose tendency is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yours or animals?
[SPEAKER_03]: Mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You could understand now, on the basis of what we described, how, like, was it...
[SPEAKER_03]: It was Gautama, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: It was his mother.
[SPEAKER_03]: When she came and asked for a brief instruction to go into the forest for the Vāsā, he says, whatever you know it's unsuitable, unwholesome, don't do it, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Don't engage with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whatever you know it's wholesome, engage with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you stick to that, on the level of body-speech-mind, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: sight-sound-smell-taste-touches-thoughts, well, it will be highly unlikely, virtually impossible, that the animal is not tamed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, see, it's wilderness, it needs fuel, it needs maintenance, it needs perpetuation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, and you're doing it,
[SPEAKER_03]: through carelessly attending to unsuitable sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you stop carelessly attending to those things, and whenever those things pop up out of your own mental habits, well, you don't lose the context, you don't lose yoniso, manasikāra, you broaden the context by presenting the bigger picture, and then the animal starts to learn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, whenever it's this, it's this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, it calms down.
[SPEAKER_03]: It stops craving, and you will know when it stops craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will know when the dog listens to you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you don't need to... hmm, how does this happen now?
[SPEAKER_03]: Let me psychologize about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's also... mind you, this is not really relevant, but it's kind of interesting, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like in the suttas, when... when, say, all the asa is abandoned, the animal is stained,
[SPEAKER_03]: There are no more, kind of, underlying tendencies there.
[SPEAKER_03]: When, it says, like, if he were to direct his mind towards the memory of the previous lives, and if there is an opening, he will remember it.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's not doing the remembering.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are not doing that.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just tell your mind to go and fetch.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the same with any memory.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the dog just goes and runs, and you wait, and it comes back after, and it fetched some memorabilia that now you remember.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the same with any memory.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, people already deep down can have a hint of the animal that's not... they're doing, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you remember?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, remembering, like, what I ate today?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah, how do you remember it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Try to remember something that you haven't already thought before you said it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Try to remember something.
[SPEAKER_02]: What I ate yesterday.
[SPEAKER_03]: What did you do ten years ago?
[SPEAKER_03]: Just remember it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Did you come up with the memory or did you just sort of ten years ago and then the memory was presented to you?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Every single time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Especially when you can't remember something and you're trying.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's when you realize how much it's not your doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, if you try too hard, that becomes a thing now, that's obstructing the animal from action.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they say, no, I have to untry a bit, and then you remember.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, then, the animal remembers it for you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, who is that you I keep talking about?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, we have determined the animal is what citta is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Who is this you that is responsible for what you feed to the animal, what you present it with?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a dialogue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yes, but how would a sutta refer to it?
[SPEAKER_02]: What would a sutta call that?
[SPEAKER_04]: The individual...
[SPEAKER_03]: Individual would be exactly... it would be like the collection, say, of all of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sādhānsamādhya touches thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the specific sense of you, I am, your point of view, what is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: In terms of the sutta classifications and terminology, what would that... what would the closest thing to that be?
[SPEAKER_01]: Five cleaning ingredients?
[SPEAKER_03]: More specific.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mano?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You were guessing, yeah?
[SPEAKER_02]: That was the first thing that came to mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is mano.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's intellect, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's exactly why Dhammapada Sutta... Dhammapada verse says that mano is the forerunner of everything unwholesome, not citta.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you realize, well, yes, sure, wholesome and wholesome craving comes from citta on account of what māna has been feeding it, what māna has been thinking, what images it has been revolving around.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is what's going to reflect back onto the animal and that's what's going to be looking at.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there you go.
[SPEAKER_03]: Finally, the difference between citta and māna has been cleared.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, once and for all.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, let's now say...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, where is the animal?
[SPEAKER_03]: In your own experience, how do you... Because, see, you can't think the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: You think you're citta, but that's obviously images which is māna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you relate?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you reveal?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you connect with with the unknown?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where do you look for it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Mood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, but see, the mood is something you're perceiving.
[SPEAKER_04]: Being aware of the general attitude
[SPEAKER_04]: In regards to whatever you are attending to or doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: And where would that be?
[SPEAKER_03]: How would you be aware of the general attitude?
[SPEAKER_04]: By reminding yourself of it, bringing it to mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the attitude, would that be something you're holding?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, that's the... that's why I'm saying it would be how you would relate to the citta, because it's something that is on the level of citta.
[SPEAKER_03]: The attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: Give me some examples of the attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any craving, any greed in... Well, yes, theoretically, any craving, any greed is in citta, but I'm asking how do you... where do you find that citta?
[SPEAKER_04]: Attitude of...
[SPEAKER_00]: You're saying in the background, where do you find your mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is your mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what I'm asking is, say, somebody asks you, how do I find my mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I reveal it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, obviously, if you think it, it's the thoughts you're thinking.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, attitude, yes, but...
[SPEAKER_03]: Attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I contemplate attitude?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I reveal my mind on account of an attitude?
[SPEAKER_03]: I think... Is there a more direct way?
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, that's what I'm...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where the kind of discomfort is, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like... Obviously, that needs some clarification, but...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, where the feeling is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's felt?
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, the mind is not the feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it can't be found apart from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you then get to, even more directly, to that can't be found apart from feeling, on account of feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: Physicality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, in a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: What does
[SPEAKER_03]: What we refer to as physicality, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: mindfulness of your form internally, what does that do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, in regard to revealing your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a contrast between...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know if I could say that that way, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, if you have
[SPEAKER_03]: Say, if you have physicality, like mindfulness of the body internally, mindfulness of that physicality internally, and feeling, felt, not just thought about, where's the citta there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Between.
[SPEAKER_02]: Between what?
[SPEAKER_02]: In that relationship.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, I mean...
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that there is a relationship.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, what, what, what, what does... What kind of relationship is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: A... unfound...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, theoretically, it's an unf...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, it's a... one that requires interrogation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, but that's irrelevant then for where citta is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what part of the relationship is relevant for which it is?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, your physicality and your feeling can help you discern very thoroughly, because you can't think it directly, citta, on account of what you discern there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, don't think it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Feel the feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: Experience the physicality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Are you referring to resistance?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I mean, it could be another approach, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, no, I'm not.
[SPEAKER_03]: Say there's a neutral feeling, you're not resisting anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: Where's the citta there?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like now, as we're talking about it, experiencing the physicality internally, feeling the feeling, what else is there?
[SPEAKER_03]: Not theoretically.
[SPEAKER_03]: What else is there specifically in your experience?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there something else?
[SPEAKER_03]: What type of feeling is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral?
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: Intention.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yes, it is intention, but I want people to come
[SPEAKER_03]: To that conclusion, in their own description and the words.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if physicality reveals, or basically, experiencing physicality internally, sets you, resets you into your situation, the general experience as a whole, the framework of it, where you can't be outside of, the present moment, quote-unquote, feeling,
[SPEAKER_03]: Being felt.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, what else?
[SPEAKER_02]: What else are you having there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Pressure towards...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why is the pressure there?
[SPEAKER_03]: Towards what?
[SPEAKER_03]: On account of what?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, there would be...
[SPEAKER_04]: If there's pressure, it would be
[SPEAKER_04]: To, like, let's say, intend something, do something, on account of a perception, something that you're... something that you're attending to, on account of... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: For example...
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: He's asking me this question, I must give an answer.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: For example.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, where is the citta there in that example?
[SPEAKER_03]: You're still not telling me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depression.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depression or citta?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's closest to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, I'm asking even more directly, accurately.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, for somebody who just started practicing, their mood is their citta.
[SPEAKER_03]: They don't see anything else subtler than that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, obviously, the more you do it, it's not.
[SPEAKER_03]: The pressure, it's not.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you see that which is invisible?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you have to see both.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if there's the feeling and the
[SPEAKER_04]: Let's say, if there's a pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: To intend.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you see both.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And?
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, seeing kind of... Well, the citta is basically like the space, quote-unquote, in between the two.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's how I put it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it doesn't need quote-unquote.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is the space.
[SPEAKER_03]: The space created through neither here nor there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the reason why that's important
[SPEAKER_03]: It's because you can be seeing the two and then coming up to see the third.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you're not going to see the third.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's going to fall on one of the two.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in order to see citta, then, you need to undo maybe 50, 60, maybe 80 percent of your craving to see the citta, in order to see it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It depends.
[SPEAKER_03]: Depends how strongly you want to see citta.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the absolute, probably most accurate, cleanest yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can have principles of it here and there, but when it comes to yoniso manasikāra, that is the only... like, there is anything coarser than that, cannot, will not reveal it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will reveal the hints of it, the signs of the mind, you know, the simile of the cook, again, beforehand, but the point is,
[SPEAKER_03]: You want to be able to directly know where it is, whenever and wherever it is, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's when you're always, well, keeping an eye on the dog, which means now you can have even more accurate timing for your instructions, for your commands, for your clickers.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, in order to see citta, you need to see both physicality and feeling,
[SPEAKER_03]: And then probably endure that for a while, until your own craving to see the citta subsides.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it would subside, because although you're not seeing the citta directly, by enduring the physicality, by experiencing the physicality with the currently enduring feeling, there is a message you're conveying to the citta that will basically calm you down, even if you're not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can we speak a little bit more about the physicality?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I've been overthinking that these past few days.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what's your body posture now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sitting.
[SPEAKER_03]: You didn't have to stand up to tell me that.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there an internal... internally felt fact?
[SPEAKER_03]: Of that seated body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is the fact that I'm sitting.
[SPEAKER_03]: But internally.
[SPEAKER_03]: Internal sense of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I mean, on the inside.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's say that.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I mean, when that fact that I'm sitting...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the fact that I'm sitting with all my focus...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not the fact that you're sitting.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the internal fact of your sitting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, the internal fact that's revealed through recognizing the fact of your external sitting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're seated.
[SPEAKER_03]: You cannot possibly doubt that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe you find a different word for it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You could doubt how to express it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that fact you can't doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: But how do you know that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you tell me you're seated, even if you close your eyes?
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you're not looking externally at your seated body.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what are you telling me then?
[SPEAKER_03]: What are you... what are you seeing when you close your eyes and I say, what's your body posture?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you... Well, let me ask you this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Close your eyes and I'll ask you, do you have a body?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you know that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where did that knowledge come from?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just something that I remember.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you remembered it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where was it before you were remembering it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Was it elsewhere?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can it be elsewhere?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can it be anywhere else but right there?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can be everywhere else.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can forget about it, distract yourself, go to great extents.
[SPEAKER_03]: But whenever you remember it, you find it where it always was.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the physicality, the internal side of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not your associated images with it, which, of course, are going to follow.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you think of your body, you're going to have images of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, as I said, even the general question, do you have a body?
[SPEAKER_00]: You already know the answer to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, do I have a body?
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, look at that internal fact of that thing there.
[SPEAKER_03]: What we described in two talks ago, when we lost one, you know, the internal gravity, or whatever you want to call it.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is a physicality.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is the situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is the framework for every other subsequent experience you might have on account of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of the being embodied, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you can say that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So the point of this is that it's not to, like, externally observe your body, but to discern that internal one.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the whole satipaṭṭhāna of body within the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: You start thinking the body and find the body, experience the body within your thoughts of that body.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when that becomes your thoughts of the body, experience further internal body in regard to those thoughts of body, to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's kind of what I was... like, just that... the tendency of kind of getting the idea of, like, oh, it's a mental image... You will.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it works.
[SPEAKER_03]: So... Everything has to basically be an image like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the point is, through discerning them rightly, you won't take them for granted.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because there is the factual physicality
[SPEAKER_03]: Always at that same place, so to speak, at that same space, that you are experiencing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in that sense, I know it's not obviously accurate, strictly speaking, but yes, you can feel that, as opposed to think it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, like you were saying earlier, that feeling is always experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: What?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, yeah, I'm just basically repeating what I was... what you just said, in the sense that... Ah, that feeling, you mean the body is always experienced?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That experience of that internal body is always there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just being covered up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Regardless of the mood, regardless of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Regardless, regardless, regardless.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the... it's... it's the container.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the basis for all of your, as I said, particular sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: That... that would be...
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, taking the pressure, for example, as a sign of the... as the mind, but then, not... that... that...
[SPEAKER_02]: There, we're taking the pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's alright.
[SPEAKER_02]: The... the uninterruptedness of feeling, feeling, will be, yeah, less perturbed, the more that, yeah, this practice of... of...
[SPEAKER_03]: Discerning the relationship between physicality of the body and... Well, yeah, but see, like, you're not... you're only discerning the relationship marginally, really.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not about the relationship.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not about discerning it in a sense of figuring it out, how it relates.
[SPEAKER_03]: It relates by being there.
[SPEAKER_03]: These two things are there.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the relationship.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yes, you do need to discern that, because for as long as you think it relates, it comes from here into there, and then it goes elsewhere, yes, of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not going to see any of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you're recognizing the just mere juxtaposition of the internal physicality and feeling felt, that's the relationship you want.
[SPEAKER_03]: But not... well, of course, discern and then really not cover up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if it's neutral.
[SPEAKER_03]: Especially.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yes, you could say there's physicality and there's neither pleasure nor pain felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Great.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, don't cover up that experience now.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's, you know, what I was saying before.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, if you have thoughts, OK, but where's my chit-chat?
[SPEAKER_03]: Include that in the experience of those two things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Don't give into it and try to resolve it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're closer to resolution by not acting out of that craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, of course, it was their very craving that brought you there.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you didn't crave to see the citta, if you were not pressured towards it, if you did not generate a desire to do so, well, you would have not have... you would have not discerned the relationship between the internal physicality and feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's kind of like... you know how the aggregate of virtue sets up a fence around the wild animal?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, this is clearly like a... another sort of... layer to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you might not know, at times, where my mind is, or discern it peripherally correctly, but you know physicality and the feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you know what has to be within that space.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why the space was relevant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cannot be outside of this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same sense, well, I don't know where my moods come from, and what they are, and how they act, and how they pressure me, but I know they cannot pressure me on account of household life, they cannot pressure me on account of sensuality, ill-will, of this coarse nature in terms of the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: They cannot, because those things have been abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Back to this physicality.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you look at Majjhima 62, you see, like, the Buddha teaching Mahārūḍa.
[SPEAKER_00]: And before he gets to ānāpānasati,
[SPEAKER_00]: He's talking about the five aggregates are not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you must see them as.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, he goes to the elements, but with specific bodily contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like whatever is internal, that is hard and solid, weight, gravity, and taken up, that is the earth element.
[SPEAKER_00]: And
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like the hair of the head.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have that... it gives you that idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hair of the head, that thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hair of the body, nails, teeth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, to me, it's... you've got to find that internal, hard, solid, corresponding aspect.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have an idea of hair of the head.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where's the corresponding hardness of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that... Where's the hardness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where's the solidity of the weight of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it... You can't... You know, you can have the idea of the word and the concept... Yeah, what is the internal solidity of it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Not external, because somebody could be touching the hair or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, internally.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to include all those images
[SPEAKER_03]: In that internal solidity... And why is that important?
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, while we're talking about it... Why is it important to say... see all the five aggregates as not mine?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or all the form, internal, external, earth, water, fire, air, to leave nothing out?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is that important?
[SPEAKER_03]: To include it in that relationship of physicality, felt.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whatever is left out is taken up as mind, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: But in terms of what we've been talking about, citta, why is it relevant for that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, of course, it's taken as mind, but in terms of this whole talk,
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is it relevant to include everything?
[SPEAKER_01]: Wait, to include it all within the relationship?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the relationship establishes, as I said, and then whatever is left out, you realize cannot be left out.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, you are intentionally unleaving it out by bringing it up on the base of physicality felt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Actually, that's a relationship, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Physicality felt.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't need to say experience physicality in the field of healing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just physicality felt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Both are already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why is it important to include things that were tacitly excluded?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it that that's important?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or just kind of if things are left out, then you're not seeing either end properly?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, so to speak, like... That is important.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, I guess, this is...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you are seeing, say, you are factually experiencing physicality, feeling felt.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, the Sutra encourages to start including all these seemingly less relevant things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, internal bile and bones and this... Why?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, to disassociate those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: From what?
[SPEAKER_04]: From the internal physicality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are kind of associating with internal physicality.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, at least.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: They are disassociated from physicality internally.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why they're left out.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you think internal physicality, you don't have the images of your bones and marrow and stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: You haven't associated them with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm going from the other direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in the context of what we've been talking about,
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind, citta, the animal, why is it important to include all these images, all these things, all these implicit... Why is it important to include the image with the physicality, essentially?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, like what you were describing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, oh, any... okay, internally... body experienced internally and starts including
[SPEAKER_03]: The hair, the nails, the extent of all of that internally.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is that relevant?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's peaceful.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, let's say like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, again, that doesn't bear any answer to citta that I'm asking.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what happens to citta if you're not including it?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if these things are not included, how does that affect?
[SPEAKER_03]: Citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not, eh... expanded, or it's narrowed, or not liberate.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: To the extent the things are not included, to that extent you won't be seeing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can think you're seeing it, but if the internal extent of that physicality is not brought up
[SPEAKER_03]: To the certain size, let's call it that way, you won't be seeing the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because mind is what's left when everything else is included of that space.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why contemplation of infinite space, if you are refined to perceive it, immediately outlines where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it won't be anywhere in the space.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, infinite space means any possible direction of space up...
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter what axis you take.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you're perceiving that on that level, you are clearly then outlining the mind for what it's not.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, as I said, for someone who just starts practicing, becoming aware of their own thoughts, including then
[SPEAKER_03]: As real phenomena, everything else, not that, will be the citta.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yeah, citta has obviously proliferated through your own... well, through your own lack of discernment.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: And for as long as citta is not clearly outlined internally, through what it is not, there's going to still be an underlying tendency to fall into the assumption
[SPEAKER_03]: That the pressure came from here, or there, or this, or that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the connection.
[SPEAKER_03]: By the way, citta can't enter your māna and your world.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's... animal is animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are you.
[SPEAKER_03]: But through not fully delineating that, not fully understanding, clearly, the difference in those two domains, one is invisible domain of the animal,
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how you basically, yourself, assume, project pressure coming out of the thoughts, or this, or that, that pertains to you, not the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like how we started this.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you have
[SPEAKER_03]: Anger, your... the thoughts to think these... pressure to think these cruel thoughts, we say, oh, well, who thinks the thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: Was it you or the animal?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, no, it's me, due to the pressure exhibited by the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there's going to be traces of that pressure left for as long as things are not sufficiently included into that physicality felt here and now.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when they are, then the mind is, how the sutra says, you know, abhāsara and bright and infinite and pure and unobstructed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Still the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Still it's going to disintegrate like everything else, so you're not holding any mystical views in regard to it, but it's factually clean, obedient, no more clickers, no more hints.
[SPEAKER_03]: It just does the right thing on its own accord every single time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Make the right choice.
[SPEAKER_03]: And how would you know, practically speaking, not from the Arahant's point of view, how would you know when on some days, like, you are not outlining your mind clearly enough?
[SPEAKER_03]: What would be the first symptom of that?
[SPEAKER_03]: And it would remain throughout, that symptom.
[SPEAKER_03]: It wouldn't disappear.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hint, we spoke about it in the last two talks.
Suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, of course, but more practically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Resistance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Resistance, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Of course, suffering, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, you know, okay, so I suffered as I resist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fighting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, fight comes out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fight comes out of resistance.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why is it important for you
[SPEAKER_03]: For your mano, to give up resistance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, in the context of citta, that we speak about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not gonna calm it down.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not... Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just punish.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can be telling it what you want, but if the dog sees that you are the one resisting it, well, then, of course, it will continue doing its own resisting and craving against it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you don't add more of the same, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you practicing the unresisting of resistance in regard to what's felt, is another way of talking to your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: However coarsely you might be doing that, you realize, oh, it's already conveying the same message that I might be doing, you know, in the future on a more subtler level.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, here and now, internal physicality felt unresisted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, add few things to that mix.
[SPEAKER_03]: Push it into that framework.
[SPEAKER_03]: Include those thoughts of this form and that form, and internal, and body, and skin, and bones, and then unresisted.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then include more, and then unresisted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, include more into the physicality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, start contemplating impermanence, destruction, cessation, and unresisted.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's also talking to your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's also telling the obvious to the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Danger.
[SPEAKER_03]: Danger, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Platification, danger, escape.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's really just presenting these rightly seen phenomena
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you don't see the mind, by having them there, the mind's seeing them.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know where the dog is.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know it's within this fence, because fence is impenetrable.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know where it is, but if I play these sounds, I know it will have to hear it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like when you're kind of prodding the elephant with spears and swords and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the suttas, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: To teach it how to not move even further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was thinking that it could also be, like we were talking a couple of talks ago, how do you gladden the mind?
[SPEAKER_04]: And that actually, maybe it's somewhat less direct, but I think bringing up, like, for example, you know, the things, like think concrete things that represent impermanence, for example.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I'm resisting that.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's kind of how to gladden it further, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: It becomes... Well, imagine, again, imagine like you're with a dog and there is something... there's a factually agitating sight for both you and the dog.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the dog is just barking and losing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can't remove the sight.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't even tell to a dog that actually there is no danger, because it's already agitated.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you just sort of, you know, pet it and show it, physically, that you are calm.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the dog will calm down.
[SPEAKER_03]: All the thing is still there, and it still might be edgy about it, but it would calm down, because you unresisted yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that was the relevance of, you know, what he's talking about in those previous two talks, was exactly that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just... Yeah, you might know, you don't... you don't necessarily see the animal that clearly, or not always, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: But factually, by unresisting yourself, again, as I said, the animal has to hear it, because you know it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: In one of the older videos, you were talking about
[SPEAKER_01]: Just this kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was in the context of this kind of overthinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, what is the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: You said it is just like the actual body there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: At least that's... that's how I remember it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does seem like that's kind of a pretty concrete way of just cutting through the...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, of course, you can take that in whichever way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, whatever sort of help a person needs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the point is to to look for it and you realize
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I find it, not by finding it, but by uncovering it, because it's already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not making it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's a sense of touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well...
[SPEAKER_03]: Start with a sense of touch, but then you have to look past it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the closest and then...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as you can see, like bodily sensations.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's the...
[SPEAKER_03]: But really, it's not really closer to the internal body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Internal body is the saḷāyatana.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, as sights are.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Smells.
[SPEAKER_03]: Smells are already touching it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sounds are already landing on it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not more closer.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just that people approach the body through the external images of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, see, what I think my body is, it's this thing here, and inside of that is these sensations and touches.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, that must be more of the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's already completely upside down.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, the whole idea of external, it's on the count of you already experiencing that physicality here and now, internally.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the framework for anything, whether it's external or then internal again.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, it's something I was thinking a while ago, but, like, at some point, I remember having the thought or realizing it's kind of completely gratuitous to think that, like, through the eyes, what I'm perceiving is the room.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then,
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, I'm perceiving my body with the sense of touch.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's like, I'm just as well perceiving the room with my body.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, that's...
[SPEAKER_03]: I think we said that before.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think even in some philosophies it was said, all you are perceiving is your senses perceiving things.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the space revealed with your eyes is secondary to your experience of eyes seeing space revealed objects.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, the minds...
[SPEAKER_03]: Through the default.
[SPEAKER_03]: Desire, non-restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, not even, as I said, not even recognizing thoughts and images to be real as such.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not seeing them as phenomena.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how you then proliferate further into that space.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then that space, externally, which you perceive, becomes a reference point back onto you, or on you, or externally.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then we're all equal, filling out this space.
[SPEAKER_03]: But all of that's secondarily proliferate experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: What your experience is,
[SPEAKER_03]: What you experience is eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body, mind, perceiving, sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are not... you do not have access to the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's what I kind of meant earlier when I think... because I thought, when you were asking about, like, including the...
[SPEAKER_04]: I was wondering about clarifying this anyway, so that's why I'm...
[SPEAKER_04]: The specific, I don't know, organs, like, I don't know, the hair on the head, or the... because... because I think what I thought you were referring to was, let's say, for example, you kind of start with these kind of, like, vague ideas or perceptions, like, and they would be kind of tactile perceptions, like, say, a perception of feet, or of knees, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_04]: That kind of stand for the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, but they're not the body.
[SPEAKER_04]: They're not the internal body.
[SPEAKER_03]: If they stand for it, they will be there and then.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, but that's...
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: It seems to me that they stand for it, basically, by not being kind of fully discerned, or not being clearly discerned as images.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, like, if I look at them, basically, I'm kind of saying this practically.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not sort of... this is not...
[SPEAKER_04]: I realize, well, actually, it can't... it can only be another level of an image.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, there's something else.
[SPEAKER_04]: There is something else, like, behind it, or below it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I think, what I understood was, like, it is kind of further clarifying or discerning more of the...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, and there is a need for that, but also, that in and of itself does not necessarily translate
[SPEAKER_03]: It certainly removes the obstructions and it probably is improving your communication with the mind, but even of itself does not necessarily result in what we've been talking about in this talk.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, no, this is slightly tangential.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yes, of course, yes, like that whole casino practice, as we said before, you could eventually
[SPEAKER_03]: You can have images of the great element of earth and planet and whatever, universe, mountains, stones, the properties of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can have images of those properties associated with your internal form, with your internal body, if you would have diligently abandoned everything else inferior to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, another more like a practical side of including the body organs here, that's basically, it is what occupies the space of the body here.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just leave it out.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you judge, as I said, the space of the body by the space of your perception, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you recognize, well, the space of the body, space of the perception, space is there and it's fully occupied to the brim.
[SPEAKER_03]: Besides sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, images of what constitutes sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, there is nothing in and out left in anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, where does... where would a citta... where does a citta correspond to, approximately, in terms of that space that your body occupies?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where would you place your citta?
[SPEAKER_04]: At the heart.
[SPEAKER_03]: Kind of in that area.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not specifically to the left or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, who knows.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why this whole contemplation of these specific images, like bones and skin and whatever, you're kind of lighting up, you know, you... Yeah, you're lighting up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're lighting up the whole kāyā.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like that first step of ānāpānasati, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, of course, of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: Experience the whole body.
[SPEAKER_03]: But by lighting up the whole kāyā, you realize it's all included.
[SPEAKER_03]: That citta is not there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by including everything, that's how you outline what's not there, which is citta.
[SPEAKER_04]: Actually, sorry, I'm now going to be slightly jumping, but you said, eh... but that was something that also occurred to me, like the... you were asking, like, where would you place your citta?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it would be kind of corresponding to the internal heart.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I was thinking that could also be, eh... what it's referring to with parimukkha,
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, I mean, even more, sort of, bringing the... Well, yeah, I think there is an overlap there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Anyway, it was kind of understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yes, there are certain convergence points.
[SPEAKER_03]: Convergence points of your own
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, means of expression, means of gaining pleasure, means of acting out, and it would be, let's say, descending upon those parts, like losing perspective in regard to everything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, you know, I don't know, like, violent people have that expression, like, oh, these hands have the mind of their own.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, when they get angry and start fighting, beating, and... as in, like, that, just, that, that's all they, that's all they see.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like, factually, your mind would have been probably descended on your limbs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, sexuality-wise, your groin, yeah, speech, your mouth.
[SPEAKER_03]: Things that are factually taken up.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by practicing un-taking up, un-resisting, from your point of view, not making citta to do it, you un-resisting those convergent points, sends a message to citta.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it can't make you double down, unless you choose to double down.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's the stealing of activations.
[SPEAKER_03]: Physical, verbal and mental stealing of taking-ups that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's still going to be taking-up that the animal's doing, but, as I said, you don't have to worry about that.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you untake-up everything to be taken-up, then the animal will not be able to remain holding for much longer.